Now I move on to gravity
I showed this Slide the properties of ellipse I just to remind you that we talked about the eccentricity and a major axis
Let's move on from there
The Chocolate War about
The properties of the ellipse
I said the sun is at one Focus Lee leafs
The closest approach
Call that perihelion
And at maximum distance from the Sun is called aphelion
And
From the centre to the edge is a distance a
From the centre to here
This was called C
And was equal to EA
He is a number less than 1
As you combine those you'll find that this
Distance to closest approach we get to
The perihelion distance is
8 * 1 - Erie is a number that's
Less than 1 is between 0 and 1
And the aphelion distance the maximum distance just using the geometry and straightforward there
Is a * 1 + 8
And you'll note of course I add this distance plus this doesn't mean you're going to be in
Tire
Major oxide is the semi-major axis a plastic semi-major axis a2a
So these two digits is always have to add up to
The two eggs that's just the definition of a major Acts
So you can always write this the minimum
Plus the maximum distance is equals to a sister
Very straightforward identity and might turn out to be useful somewhere
And if you were to look up here and look at this and know this plus this you will find that in fact
Does a -80 * 8 + 3 * 8 can select ended up with a plus a witch gives
Can obviously the same thing
Turns out you Wausau
Newton's equations that show the orbits are an ellipse
Critical point in this
Is the centre of mass now I'm not going to do the calculations but I have another reason for showing the centre of mass
Because the size of the orbits
Depend on
The masses of the objects
So if you're doing the calculations to
To work out with the orbits look like
Rattling doing two separate bodies
Play a star and a planet in orbit around each other
And trying to solve two different sets of orbits
It's much more to me to move into a different reference frame
And reference frame that's useful is look
Center of mass reference frame
Do you have to deal with all the other emotions that these two things might be doing
And in fact she look at the centre of mass reference frame that is
The distance from the centre of Mass to the star
Is A1 and this is to this other star or could be a planet a to the sum of the two is the distance between
In the two stars
It turns out if they're not of equal Mass the centre of mass of course is closer to the more massive thing so here's a free stamp
Michael has a mass 2m has a mass of 1 M and A Center of mass
Is somewhat to the left
And
The centre of mass position that's
Does A1 and A2
Describe it
Is given by this equation M1 A1
Pecos m-28
Juices always balance
M1 is larger a one is smaller
So
Dealt with this before sort of I said that we had was Kepler's third law where we had
A relationship between. And
Semi-major axis. Squared is equal to 7 major axis
Cute but that was a very specific case in fact that's
Only really true
That particular version of the equation
When you have a very massive object like the sun
And a very low Mass Ave
Chip like
A planet
Because the centre of mass is essentially in the Sun
In the sun more or less looks like it's fixed at the centre of mass
So it's not really too much ambiguity as to when your measuring from one place to another what we really shouldn't measuring from is the centre of mass
Direct me someplace with other objects for example where there's two stars with one of those not of negative Mass
This is a form of Kepler's Law that you're going to end up with
Again I'm not driving all this for you I'm just trying to give you a few definition
So if you have a case where you're dealing with a
A star that is twice the mass of the sun we caught a 2 solar mass star
Plus another star in orbit around it that saw
1 solar mass star very similar to our sun
Then you could write the equation this winning numbers would actually come out you can write in
2 solar masses + 1 solar mass
Times of. Squared in years
Because we doing everything in solar masses
And we do this any major axis in astronomical units even though it's another pair of stars out there
Play write the sum of these distances
From the centre of mass and the sum of these two chords
Is the separation between the two stars
We actually measure the separation between the two
And this is the version of Kepler's Law you get
I can song this is an astronomical units in this isn't solar masses
This is what you would use it turns out it's just coming pretty from this definition of Center Mass and doing the derivation
What would the orbits look like
They're going around the centre of mass
Retrieve them each separately go around the centre of mass
And
Instead of having to make one go around the other and trying to work up the
Situations which is very complicated we're making music around some common Center of mass
Here's if they have the
Identical masses you'll find there's two identical
Orbitz
Each civista Arthur
Identical masses and it's just the mass
Determined sayings
There's a
Common Focus here
So each of these objects each of these Stars
Is an orbit
In an ellipse
Where
There is a common Focus this comment focus is the centre of mass
The system
In our solar system Kepler saw was he said
That the sun was at one Focus
He wasn't quite right
Okay the sun was really close to 1/4
If I have to focus
Inside the
Not the centre of the Sun
But
Somewhere inside the side cuz the sun is so massive
You'll notice that a Time 1
Stars must be
On opposite sides
APA Sentra Mass otherwise what does it mean to be the centre of mass
So that means that the centre of mass here
Is always equidistant between easy
Because these two are the same masks
So when the stars are very far away from the
Focus
Is the part of the motion where they're moving slowly and its elliptical orbit then they're both moving slowly
I'm going to come down here and move
Close to this common Focus the centre of mass
They're both moving fast
Tree both stars are moving very fast
So this is in fact that the orbits would look like if we did the whole mathematical treatments in centre of Mass frame and look at each star separate into the
Calculation
We find it we got something like a seahorse have to do something called reduce Mass make it all work
Sort it all out
That's straightforward
So here's a case where you have
I am one here has two in a really massive one
It doesn't move very much
It's The more mass of one
The last mass of one has a much larger orbit
And they're both the gang moving around this
Common Focus
Center of mass
If you were to have a really large mass as in
The sun compared to planets
Then here's the Sun and you can see the sun's orbit
Around the centre mass is smaller than Tire motion of the Sun
Is smaller than the radius of the Sun
The sun's orbit is entirely within the Sun
Because it's so much more massive than any of the planets
Which we have large planet orbits
And a very small orbit for the Sun
There is a centre of mass of the entire solar system
And
We're going to calculate all the motions
As orbits around the solar system
Barry
Center
So there is the Sun
And that red
Diamond is the
Center of mass of our solar
Notice the time is moving really fast up here
So notice that.
Sutter the mass of the solar system was inside the Sun for a few moments
Just a point
Center Mass
The solar system is primarily defined by the
Sun
But the next biggest
Thing that is important
Jupiter
So the main motions you're seeing of the sun are the Sun moving in reflex
The Jupiter
What emotion is complicated because there's lots of other planets in our solar
Besides being dragged around by all the planets in
In the solar system is so ends up with his rather complicated
But when you're doing the mathematical derivation
One of the fundamental equations that we use as we use the conservation of energy
And that has many other places in this course we're a conservation and she's going to be a third of a critical thing trying to understand what happens in fact
The entire evolution of
Have our son for exact was an exercise in conservation of energy
Entire universe evolves because of problems in the conservation of energy
The sun is shining
Shining means it's losing energy
Something has to change
Can the Sun cause losing energy to can't do that forever
That the fundamental driving thing for every stars stars shine so they have to change
Because they have to evolve because they are
Not conserving energy they need a new source of energy
Keep on Shining
Play energy can never be
Created or destroyed
Energy changes form as it moves between objects you can convert it to Mass
The total mass energy
Content combined
All the universe
Hasn't changed remains
The same now it's
Moved around
Kinetic energy is a good starting spot we're trying to talk about motion
Orbit so kinetic energy is the most relevant energy
1/2 MV squared
You might remember the Newton's law of gravity had the force was
Gravitational constant
Capital G
* M1 mass of one object
M to the mass of another object
Divided by the distance
Between them
Square
That's the for slaw
Turns out that the energy that goes with that we called gravitational potential energy
At almost the same thing except there's a negative sign in front and it's not r squared it's r
This is the energy
But things have in a gravitational field
This is the kinetic energy they have if they're moving
These two equations combined give you all kinds of
Useful things that you can do about orbits as you will see in a few moments
Notice that this is negative
If R is really really big
1 / R is really really small and this
Become 0 psi at Infinity very large distances
The potential energy is zero
Hazard gets
Smaller and smaller this number becomes bigger and bigger negative it becomes more and more negative
So it's not getting bigger is getting more negative affect getting
Smaller
Soda Springs
Come close together
That potential energy becomes
Smaller
Last has less energy
Well
Where does it go energy can't be destroyed
In terms of the interviews were talking about the only energy that we have potential energy and kinetic energy
The sum of them
If you add up all the energy
It's a constant energy doesn't change
So we can just write it that way
Potential energy
Which was the you
And the kinetic energy added together is a constant
If there's no outside forces pushing
What does that mean I just said the potential energy Falls
Decrease is when things come closer together
That means that kinetic energy must increase
This type of energy plus this type of energy is a constant
And one of them gets smaller
The other one has to get bigger or us not
Adding up to a concert
In that case of this motion is gravitational motion of
Objects around the Sun or other kind of orbit
We know that it's faster at some points in its orbit
Play close to the Sun and its Lord other points
So the kinetic energy is changing
Where does energy go 1/4 goes into gravitational potential energy
As it was further and further from the Sun we slow down and lose kinetic energy what we gain potential energy
We're moving at the slowest point when we're far from the Sun at this particular instead
When we're at aphelion moving at right angles to the Sun and then the motion isn't quite circular down hearing it
Closest point at perihelion were also moving
At right angles to the Sun
But not at all these other points Harris not quite perpendicular
The other
Useful conserved quantity
Which comes into doing orbits but going to come into when I start talking about the formation of the solar system information Stars
This is the
Limiting principle this is that thing that really
Governance what we see Willy
Pornstars about this is why we have a solar
Because of conservation of angular momentum
That wasn't a conserved quantity
Everything will be spiritually would have nothing flat and we have no flat and disc
The planets
Things like that
So spin is a conserved quantity conservation of angular momentum
The symbol for angular momentum is a capital l
Are equals the mass
Times the speed
X the distance so
The momentum depends on
The mass of this object the speed it's moving at and the distance away and in fact has the speed perpendicular
Tua radius that's the ACT
Allstate that matters
And if there's no outside forces acting on an object this is a conserved quantity it doesn't change
So that means if
Is Alice a concert if the distance becomes smaller
Is only the mass doesn't change the speed must become greater
So whenever an object that orbits at CineLux for example
When it moves in closer
The distance is smaller the speed has to be figure that's
In fact why
The speed is larger when you're at perihelion and aphelion light mention this last day when I
First Choice shop
Lots of examples of anger mentum
Both the people who what do flips in the air on skis and I'm boards
And then also the figure skaters
If you put your hands out when you're spinning you slow down because
You're moving more mass out to a larger distance
You bring your hands in and you're spinning you will spin faster
Because if by making the distance small you make the
Speed large
And so this is a very familiar estimate we've seen many times before
Special Sports things
And I've already said that as you're at smaller dispensation move faster larger Arrow here because of conservation of air
Sacramento
Inaka derivation but I will point out that this is what you would get
If you take Newton's law of gravity
And the conservation of angular momentum
And you just
Do the algebra
You got an equation that relates the.
To the semi-major axis
This is the one you've already seen
. is related to the semi-major axis. Squared and a major axis
Cute
And the first version the clinic Kepler saw he just said they were related to each other
If you used to write unit solar constant was one
Videos years on the lap
An astronomical units here than it was in a square brackets had a value of 1
If you have something where the masses are
Very different from the master
If you got
Two stars for example
You could just do it in solar masses an astronomical unit
But if you want to do it in proper
Scientific unit seal metres and kilograms and things like that this is the full correct formula
Gravitational constant for Newton's Law
The mass here in kilograms for two objects and is a 4 pi squared
Set the full General version
Capitals
Third law
About if you take
Conservation energy
And gravity and just saw through 4th all the forces involved
There's a force that has to do with keeping things in in circular motion centripetal force
Not even try to get into the physics of that
If you add in conservation of energy
That's not part of Kepler's Third Law
Curad and conservation energy
And do lots of lots of math not hard but it is a page of algebra
You come up with this equation which is essentially
Equation governing the velocity
Speed
This is a velocity
At any
Point in the orbit it is not the perpendicular Veloster anything like that it's just
Travelocity
Velocity
With kinetic energy
And this is an energy equation and essentially
It's looking at the kinetic energy to
What's a century the potential energy on this side
That's where it comes from
Depart of derivation equation
So this tells you
For a particular size of orbit Asus any major accident tells you how big the orbit is
The masses are fixed the gravitational constant us fix
But as you move around in that orbit
You're at different distances from
The focus
So are here the distance from the centre of mass of the focus of the orbit
And this is the velocity
You can compute it anywhere anymore but just know
Where you are in your bed how far away are you from
From the focus of the orbiting for the solar system
That's really straightforward is how far you away from the Sun this is the distance from the Sun
This is the size of the orbit
And you can
Calculate the velocity at any point
For the Earth go around the Sun
Are is one astronomical unit AU is one astronomical unit
So this becomes
2 /
1 - 1/1 this becomes
1 / one astronomical unit
And because it's
Speed of the Earth around the Sun
It's pretty much a contest
Anesthetic conservation equation
Assassin thrown in with Kepler's Law has been driving you come up with us
Conservation
Equation state
So just to summarize three versions of Kepler's Law
The one that's
Pretty useful for our solar system
If you're going to work a little bit more gentle work in solar masses and distance in AU sand
Time in years
And here's the most General with the regular
Scientific unit